<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Honourable the Commons of England assembled in Parliament a short account of one of the grand grievances of the nation / humbly presented by James Whiston.</title>
            <author>Whiston, James, 1637?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51915</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65666)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51915)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:15 or 21242:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Honourable the Commons of England assembled in Parliament a short account of one of the grand grievances of the nation / humbly presented by James Whiston.</title>
                  <author>Whiston, James, 1637?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Appealing for the cessation of sale of public offices.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in Huntington Library and British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political corruption --  England.</term>
               <term>Sale of public office --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51915:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE THE <hi>Commons of England</hi> ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Short Account of One of the Grand Grievances of the Nation, Humbly Preſented by <hi>James Whiſton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>With Submiſſion to your Honours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT State or City which would preſerve it ſelf in good Order, and free from the diſturbances of Ill Government, muſt cheriſh the juſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments and Accuſations of the People, againſt thoſe who contrary to Law, through Ambition, Avarice, Pride, Cruelty, Oppreſſion, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, Violation or Corruption of Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeek to deſtroy their Liberties, Properties and Right, which have long been a very ſevere Judgment over this Nation. But now by God's Mercy, the Extraordinary Goodneſs of Our King, and Your Great Prudence, We hope to ſee the many Grievances (which this Land Mourns under) redreſſed; Illegal proceedings puniſh'd; and Oppreſſion ſo diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, that ſucceeding Times ſhall not dare to barter Juſtice for Gold, nor ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice our Priviledges to Riot, nor truck away the Liberty of their Countrey for a little Court Holy-Water.</p>
            <p>The Nation being thus redreſt and ſecured againſt Tyranny and Oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it will not only divert God's Judgments which hang over its head, but greatly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their Riches, increaſe the Inhabitants, and thereby much leſſen the burthen of Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot ſure be cenſured as unſeaſonable (becauſe always juſt and neceſſary) to remind this Honourable Houſe, in whoſe power only the Remedy lies, of an eminent Inconvenience to the Nation, which is the Sale of Publick Offices; In reference to which, I ſhall chiefly confine my ſelf at preſent to the Honourable City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Envy of <hi>Europe, Rome</hi>'s Terrour, <hi>England</hi>'s Heart, where the Vital Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits circulate, and the Grand Pattern by whoſe Meaſures ſmaller Corporations are apt to make their Precedents.</p>
            <p>That which I therefore humbly offer to Conſideration is, That 'tis Diſhonourable and of very dangerous Conſequence, to Expoſe publick Offices and Places to Sale. For it deflowr's the Virgin Purity of Juſtice by ſtopping the Avenues that lead to her Palace, with Mercenary Encumbrances, Expoſes the Purchaſers to almoſt inevitable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51915:2"/>Temptations, and gives an inlet and plauſible Colour for deſending Injuſtice, Bribery, Extortion and Oppreſſion. But to double and treble the value, to manage them for the beſt advantage of the Seller, and to put him upon the Rack of Improvement too; what is it but to beſpeak the unfitteſt Men, either through want of Honeſty or Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that we can meet with, to manage theſe Affairs and Places in which Juſtice, Reaſon and Prudence, require the moſt upright and moſt judicious perſons that can be procured.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Fees of Attorney's, Clerks, Serjeants, Goalers, &amp;c. in the Courts of <hi>London</hi> are vaſtly raiſed, through the increaſe of Injuſtice, by reaſon of the too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, malicious and impertinent Actions, and general Corruption among them: Yet no Magiſtrate ought from thence to raiſe the value of an unlawful Sale, becauſe he finds a numerous ſort of People thriving and doing well, by living and doing ill. And the ſame Reaſon holds againſt the Keepers of Priſons, who would never give ſuch Exceſſive Rates for their Places; nor could they live at ſuch an extravagant height of Pride were they not wicked Grinders of the Poor; Men that lay the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of their Advantage upon the Calamities of the Miſerable; at which the Magiſtrate may truly be ſaid too too much to connive, who ſuffers his Coffers to be fill'd with theſe Golden Temptations, becauſe he ſees them cloathed ſo rich, and grow ſo Fat upon the Ruines of the Unfortunate; which is quite contrary to the Office of the true Magiſtrate, who ought to have a careful Eye upon the growth of Oppreſſion, to curb and remove the Exorbitancies of Injuſtice, and to Sear away the proud Fleſh of Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Rapine, and not to ſell Impunity to the Evil-doer. Therefore it is not to be queſtion'd, That whoever receives Money for any publick Place, ſuch Perſon does but receive a publick Bribe, which only Cuſtom, and perhaps too common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance juſtifies. For never any Man, came to any Office by Money, but he was forced to exerciſe his Authority wickedly and unjuſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that buys muſt ſell, or he loſes by the Bargain Which makes the publick Offices of <hi>London,</hi> like Briars, to which Sheep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing for ſhelter, loſe a Lock.</p>
            <p>If an Appeal be made to Holy Scripture, there is moſt certainly no Learning under the Sun ſo Chymical, that can extract the leaſt drop of Authority from thence, for the Sale of publick Juſtice or its Dependencies; but exceſſive penalties it may find e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, upon all manner of Extortion, and upon all thoſe that connive at, and ſuffer it; ſo ſeverely menaced, and ſo truly threatned by Him that never fails to perform, that nothing but a fatal Irony can excuſe the contempt and neglect thereof, as if the Ears of Profit could not hear the Cries of the Poor for the thundering Noiſe of God's Judgments, ſo ſeverely denounc'd on their behalf. However they who require more particular ſatisfaction, may read that Excellent Oration of the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> which he made upon the Reſignation of his Government.</p>
            <p>Being thus Baniſhed from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> this Tenent finds no better Entertainment among the Heathen, with whom we find theſe two Maxims, like two Golden Pillars ſupporting the moſt flouriſhing, and moſt Victorious Cities in the VVorld, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath not been a little Induſtrious to maintain. Firſt, <hi>That the Sale of Offices is the greateſt wrong that can be offer'd to a Commonwealth.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That Money ought not to buy thoſe Places, which may, nay ought to be the Reward of Virtue, and are the fitteſt means to ſupply the Neceſſities of Good Men.</hi> The Sale of Offices in the flouriſhing times of the <hi>Athenians</hi> was abominated, and by the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monidns</hi> exploded as a Crime: and the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in its Increaſe and flouriſhing Condition, fined and puniſhed thoſe that ſought Offices unjuſtly; and they then firſt foſtred Diſſention among themſelves, and their own Deſtruction, when they brook'd ſo patiently the <hi>Sardonic</hi> Scoff of <hi>Jugurth, All things at</hi> Rome <hi>are to be had for Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, the <hi>Perſian Cambyſes</hi> had been too ſevere, when he flead one of his Judges for Extortion, had he ſold him his Place, much more had he farm'd it to him at a rack Rent: Nor can we believe the ſame Judge's Son would have given an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted ſum to ſit upon his Father's Skin, which he was forc'd to receive for his Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being placed in his Father's Room, to terrifie him from the ſame Offence, which the King then told him would deſerve the ſame Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>I might here repeat more of Hiſtory, but my deſign is not Prolixity. To aſcend then from Hiſtory to Reaſon, we meet with a Theſis fairly bordering upon the Law of Nature, as undeniable as Truth it ſelf; That there is nothing arms a Purchaſer
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51915:2"/>with a more confident defence of his unjuſt Dealings, than Money given for an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. It makes him that he bluſhes not to be accuſed of Rigor and Extortion, to be arraigned for Violence, nor values he the Frowns of Magiſtracy, while with a daring Forehead he is able to upbraid his Superiour, telling him, he had not his Place for Nothing, but paid ſoundly for it, and therefore hopes he ſhall not be debarr'd from making the beſt Advantage of what he has purchas'd at ſo dear a Rate. A Thing ſo obvious, that reprove him never ſo ſharply, never ſo ſeverely, it ſeems Colluſive and meerly Combination, ſo little does it ſignifie. For turn him out of Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and the Succeeding Chapman is diſcouraged. Nor does the Judge himſelf eſcape the ſmutty cenſure of Self-Intereſt and Partiality, that he only removes the old One in hopes of a better bargain from a Succeſſor, that muſt be worſe becauſe he gives more for it. Here Juſtice may be ſaid to be throughly Blind, while the Seller and Abetter throw away the Vail of Impartiality, and preſs down their Eyelids with their own Fingers. Thus, Firſt rate Offences, Miſdemeanours of the upper Form, muſt be conniv'd at and palliated, for fear of ſpoiling the Market. As for Peccadilloes, and petty Oppreſſions, they are little or not at all regarded. Yet theſe are the little Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine that inſenſibly devour the Poor and Needy, that have moſt need of Succour. VVhat is the difference between the Canker that indiſcernably conſumes, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive ſpeed of <hi>Aqua Fortis?</hi> They both deſtroy: But the Canker far more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly, as being leſs attended by the hand of Care and Preſervation. A Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour of <hi>Three Hundred Pound</hi> makes a great Noiſe; yet proves perhaps but ſingly fatal, when the ſame Sum divided into Crown Rapines ſhall deſtroy as many indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual neceſſitous Families, impoveriſhed before and altogether helpleſs, without creating any other ſounds but thoſe of <hi>neglected Lamentations.</hi> So that the Sale of ſuch Offices is poſitively againſt the <hi>Tenth Commandment;</hi> as alſo againſt the ſeveral Laws of the Land (as hereafter will appear). For what greater Injury can a man do his Neighbour, than to deprive him of the greateſt Right that is due to him? To debar him of that Juſtice which ought to be afforded him in his Extremity? And not only in this manner to injure his Neighbour, but his poor Neighbour too, the <hi>particular Client</hi> of God himſelf? For remedy of which the Supreme <hi>Legiſlator</hi> made no Law, but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Admonitions, as if Man could not be guilty of ſo great an Impiety as to rob the Spittle, which is an accumulated Murther. It is injurious to him that ſells: for how can he reach forth his hand to receive the free boons of Mercy from the God of Pity and Compaſſion, while polluted with the Price of Rapine, Violence and Injury?</p>
            <p>The Sale of the Keepers Places of <hi>Ludgate, Newgate,</hi> with the <hi>Compters,</hi> &amp;c. and the unexpreſſible extravagant Extortion they make thereby, brings me to urge this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little cloſer; which are at <hi>Who gives most?</hi> An hainous Demand in the Barter of thoſe <hi>Shops of Cruelty!</hi> A ſtrange piece of abſurd Severity! To ſell the Freedom of a Captive; An Uſurpation certainly beyond Law (to ſell that little Liberty which the Law has left a Priſoner) to the diſpoſal of a <hi>Turnkey.</hi> The Law makes him a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to his Creditor, and the Magiſtrate afterwards ſurrenders him up for Money a Slave to his worſe than <hi>Argier-Keeper?</hi> Shall the Publick Houſes built at the Cities Charge be ſold for private Lucre? So that every Room in a priſon becomes a ſhop of <hi>Barbariſm</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Power, where the chief <hi>Baſha</hi> of Iniquity Exerciſes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Tyranny, and ſqueezes the very <hi>Faeces</hi> and <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> of a periſh'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as long as the leaſt drop will come, by the ſame Art as they fetch Oyl out of Bricks; firſt heating the poor Priſoner in the Fire of his threatning Indignation, and then quenching him again in the ſweet ſhow of a little Favour, while any moiſture of Gain appears.</p>
            <p>Here then lies the force of the <hi>Dilemma;</hi> Either a Priſoner for Debt may be injured in Priſon, or not. Either the Injuries repeated, are Injuries, or none. If the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative be allow'd; then all that has been already ſaid has been to no purpoſe, and <hi>Holy Writ</hi> might have been more ſparing of its Exhortations. If the Affirmative be aſſerted, then he that ſells a Goaler's Place, &amp;c. ſells the Liberty, the Eſtate, the Perſon, nay, the very Lives of the Priſoners under his Juriſdiction, ſeeing that through the Cruelty of their Keepers ſo many poor people have been ſtript to their naked Skins, and when all was gone, have been ſuffocated in Holes and Dungeons, to the loſs of many of their Lives, Diſhonour of our Nation, and Scandal of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51915:3"/>
            <p>But the Civil Law, to which our own has nothing repugnant, informs us in the very words of that great Lawyer <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian,</hi> That a Priſon is a place of <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> and not of <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> That a Priſon, where there is Hunger and Thirſt is no Priſon, but a place of <hi>Torture.</hi> That no ſevere or bad Uſage is there to be admitted, where the Perſon in debt remains, not as a Slave, but only as a pledge and ſecurity for the Creditor's ſatisfaction. For which reaſon the Emperour <hi>Honorius</hi> affirmed, that it was the principal Duty of a Judge, to be frequently inform'd by the priſoners them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the ſtate of their Captivity, that no Office of Humanity might be wanting to men lockt up in Confinement. And ſo merciful were thoſe Times, that if a priſoner died in Priſon, the Law preſum'd it the fault of the Keeper, who was not to deny either Food or Bedding to the perſon in Cuſtody.</p>
            <p>But purchas'd Cruelty is now grown ſo bold, that if poor Men pay not Extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Fees and rack't Chamber-rent, they ſhall be crouded into Holes and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to be devour'd by Famine, Lice and Diſeaſes. Which being ſo undeniable, I appeal to the Tribunal of Juſtice it ſelf, by what Law, or by what Authority, not claiming under the bad Title of Illegal Cuſtom, any Sheriff, who is the immediate Goaler himſelf, and ought to receive the Cuſtody of the Priſoner <hi>Gratis,</hi> can ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly preſume to ſell the Deputation of any Man's Liberty and Life to the Comptrol of ſordid and imperious Avarice.</p>
            <p>I would fain know, by what ſurmiſe of Common Senſe a <hi>Keeper</hi> of a <hi>Priſon,</hi> can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Recompence or Fee from a Priſoner for detaining him in Priſon? There is an Admiſſion-Fee, he cries. Alas! How is man fallen from the Image of God and his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to believe that any Perſon can deſerve a Reward for only opening the door of Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Deſtruction to annoy his Neighbour and common Friend? For being ſo kind as to admit him into the horrid Grave of Impriſonment? There is a Diſ-miſſion Fee too, but this altogether as abſurd, to demand Money for letting him go that the Law has ſet free; for opening the Door to let him out of Cuſtody whom the Receiver ought not to detain. For his Care in the Interim, let them pay him that ſet him at work. The Priſoner is no way beholding to him for his Care: for 'tis that which he deſires to be without. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaies the <hi>Civil Law</hi> in this Caſe, if there be any thing due to a Keeper, it is due from the Creditor, whoſe duty it is to afford Nouriſhment and other Supports of Life to him whom he keeps in Priſon; and therefore the <hi>Keeper</hi> might refuſe to take the Priſoner into Cuſtody, till he had bargain'd with the <hi>Creditor</hi> for the Priſoner's Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as may be obſerved out of the Antient Volumns of the moſt Learned Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But now ſuch is the Confidence of a Purchaſer, that to regain his purchaſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and maintain himſelf and his Family beſides in Luxury, Pride and Idleneſs, he ſells his Taphouſe at prodigious Rates; ſo that where poor men ought to have beſt and cheapeſt, they have the worſt in Quality, and the ſmalleſt in Quantity, which makes the price exceſſive. He Farms his Beds to meer <hi>Harpies,</hi> and his great Key to ſuch pieces of imeprious Cruelty as are the worſt of Mankind. And it is a ſhame to repeat the daily Inſolencies and Indignities, which the Priſoners and their Friends are forc'd to receive at their hands. But ſee, I pray! whither will not lewd Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents at laſt lead us? It will perhaps be thought impertinent to diſpute a Goalers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for admitting us into his loathſome Manſions, when even the Common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, no doubt encouraged by ſuch Examples, will ſcarce give a Malefactor a Caſt of his Office without a Bribe, demands very formally his Fees, forſooth, of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be executed, and higgles with him too as nicely as if he were going to do him ſome mighty kindneſs.</p>
            <p>There be thoſe that ſay the Dignity of the City Magiſtrate is by the Sale of Offices ſupported. But with what diſhonour do theſe Men revile the City, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the City, at the ſame time? For ſo careful is the City to elect Men of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates proportionable to there Dignity, that there is no need of any ſiniſter Aſſiſtance to maintain the City Grandeur. No ill got Gains, but Mercy, Juſtice and upright Prudence, are the Supports of a City. Is it not a goodly ſight to ſee the Tears of the Poor, congealed by a Froſt of neglected Charity and Injuſtice into a Pearl, glittering in the Ears of ſuch or ſuch a Lady? To behold the Scarlet of the Receiver's Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy died with the Blood of helpleſs <hi>Innocents,</hi> or the purchaſe of <hi>Extortion?</hi> To
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51915:3"/>ſee one of the Chief Puniſhers of Iniquity drinking Healths of forgetful plenty in <hi>Four Hundred Pound Goblets,</hi> the price of his own Infamy, and a Serjeant's Roguery? Such ſights as theſe perhaps we can only by Conjecture gheſs at, but the All-ſeeing Eye of Heaven beholds all theſe <hi>Blind Bargains,</hi> and it is the ſame thing whether the Accompt fall heavy on the Receiver or his Offspring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> is a City whoſe Government deſervedly challenges the Preeminence of any City now flouriſhing throughout the Univerſe. <hi>Rome</hi> the Miſtreſs of the World could not Conquer her ſelf; but oftentimes lay weltring in the Blood of her own <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens;</hi> nor could ſhe hinder her own ſtreets from being the Stage, whereonſo many diſmal Tragedies of Inteſtine Diſcord were Acted. Hear the reaſon from the Words of one of her own Poets.</p>
            <q>
               <l>'Cauſe then they Juſtice baſely Bought and Sold,</l>
               <l>And Ancient Virtue was poſtpon'd to Gold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But <hi>London</hi> has been bleſs'd with ſuch a continued Calm of Peace for ſo many Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies of Years, that never any City yet enjoy'd. Is it not great pity that ſo harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a piece of Politick Government ſhould be diſturb'd and diſorder'd by violent Uſurpation? <hi>Rome</hi> was only rich with the prey of Rapine, wealthy in the Trophies of ſucceſsful Ambition: But <hi>London</hi> ſhines a famous Pile, Opulent in the Gains of honeſt Induſtry. <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Mart</hi> of War and Slaughter, <hi>London, Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>Nobile Emporium.</hi> But damn up the Current of her <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> ſell her ſeats of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and how will all her ſplendor be Eclips'd? <hi>Rome</hi> had only the dim Lamps of Morality, the obſcure Lights of ſententious <hi>Epicuriſm</hi> and <hi>Stoiciſm</hi> to guide and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct her: But <hi>London</hi> enjoys the moſt Orient Beams, the moſt unclouded Sunſhine of Divine Truth and Doctrine. I am unwilling to urge it any farther. <hi>Rome</hi> was a City, than which there was none in the World more careful to relieve the poverty of her Citizens, of which in the times of her Innocence ſhe had many. No queſtion but in <hi>London</hi> there are many Good Men that unavoidably fall to decay: Where could the City beſtow her places more Honourably than upon ſuch? What could the City ſpeak more Magnificent in Hiſtory, than to boaſt that the very Train of her Magiſtracy was ſufficient to ſupport the chiefeſt and choiceſt of her decay'd Members, content with the Lawful and Modeſt Gains of their Employments? But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry what more diſhonourable than to ſell her poor Citizens to be Dilaniated and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerated by the hand of Injuſtice, and for Money to make ſlaughterhouſes and ſhambles of her Houſes of Reſtraint? For a City ſo fairly deckt with the precious Jewels of Freedom and Priviledge to ſell the laſt remains of a Priſoners Comfort?</p>
            <p>This Honourable Houſe therefore being thus truly inform'd of theſe Abuſes, has from hence ſufficient Grounds to make a farther Inſpection into theſe crying Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And from whence can we expect Redreſs, but from thoſe Noble and Worthy Patriots, who have already made ſo fair a progreſs toward a thorough Reformation of the paſt Miſcarriages of a Corrupt and Arbitrary Government. And indeed it would be a Crime to think that They who ſit with ſuch a ſteady reſolution to re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the long neglected Order of Law and Juſtice, will omit the utter Eradicating of whatever their Great Wiſdoms ſhall judge pernicious to their Grand Deſign. So that it would be a high breach of Manners to preſs the farther Conſideration of this affair to this Auguſt Aſſembly, otherwiſe than by laying before your Honours a ſhort view of thoſe Laws already in force againſt the Sale of Offices, wherein is alſo contain'd a recital of the Laws againſt the Sale of Publick Offices already provided by our Anceſtors, as alſo of the Jaylors and other Officers Fees, with their ſeveral Duties to the Priſoners. Which though ſo ſtrongly penn'd, have hitherto, through the prevailing power of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Injuſtice, been little or not at all regarded.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51915:4"/>
               <head>This ACT was made <hi>Anno 5.6.</hi> Edw. <hi>6.</hi> Cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Penalty for Buying or Selling of ſome ſort of Offices for the avoiding of Corruption which may hereafter happen to be in the Officer and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in thoſe Courts, Places or Rooms, wherein there is requiſite to be had the true Adminiſtration of Juſtice, or Services of Truſt, and to the intent that Perſons Worthy and Meet to be advanced to the Place where Juſtice is to be Miniſtred or any Service of Truſt executed, ſhould hereafter be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the ſame, and no other.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore Enacted by the King our Sovereign Lord, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That if any Perſon or Perſons at any time here-after Bargain or Sell any Office or Offices, or Deputation of any Office or Offices, or any Part or Parcel of any of them, or receive, have, or take any Money or Fee, Reward, or any other profit directly or indirectly, or take any Promiſe, Agreement, Covenant, Bond, or any aſſurance, to receive or have any Money, Fee, Reward, or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit directly or indirectly, for any Office or Offices, or for the Deputation of any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Offices, or any part of them, or to the intent that any Perſon ſhould have, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe or enjoy, any Office or Offices, or the Deputation of any Office or Offices, or any part of any of them, which Office or Offices, or any part or parcel of them, ſhall in any wiſe touch or concern the Adminiſtration or Execution of Juſtice, or the Receipt, Comptrolment, or Payment of any of the Kings Highneſs Treaſure, Money, Rent, Revenue, Account, Aulneage, Auditorſhip, or Surveying of any of the Kings Majeſties Honours, Caſtles, Mannors, Lands, Tenements, Woods, or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; or any the Kings Majeſties Cuſtoms, or any Adminiſtration or neceſſary At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to be had, done or executed in any of the Kings Majeſties Cuſtom-Houſe or Houſes, the keeping of any of the Kings Majeſties Towns, Caſtles or Fortreſſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed Occupied or appointed for a Place of ſtrength and defence, or which ſhall concern or touch any Clarkſhip to be Occupied in any manner of Court of Record, wherein Juſtice is to be Miniſtred: That then all and every ſuch Perſon and Perſons that ſhall ſo Bargain or Sell any of the ſaid Office or Offices, Deputation or Deputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or that ſhall take any Money, Fee, Reward, or profit for any of the ſaid Office or Offices, Deputation or Deputations, of any of the ſaid Offices, or any part of any of them, or that ſhall take any Promiſe, Covenant, Bond, or Aſſurance for any Money, Reward or profit to be given for any of the ſaid Offices, Deputation or Deputations of any of the ſaid Office or Offices, or any part of any of them, ſhall not only loſe and forfeit all His and Their Right, Intereſt and Eſtate, which ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſhall then have, of, in or to any of the ſaid Office or Offices, Deputation or Deputations, or any part of any of them, or of, in, or to the Gift or Nomination of any of the ſaid Office or Offices, Deputation or Deputations, for the which Office or Offices, or for the Deputation or Deputations of which Office or Offices; or for any part of any of them, any ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſhall ſo make any Bargain or Sale, or take, receive any Sum of Money, Fee, Reward or profit, or any promiſe, Covenant or Aſſurance to have or receive any Fee, Reward, Mony or profit: But alſo that all and every ſuch Perſon or Perſons, that ſhall give or pay any Sum of Money, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or Fee, or ſhall make any Promiſe, Agreement, Bond or Aſſurance for any of the ſaid Offices, or for the Deputation or Deputations of any of the ſaid Office or Offices, or any part of any of them, ſhall immediately by and upon the ſame Fee,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51915:4"/>Money or Reward given or paid, or upon any ſuch Promiſe, Covenant, Bond or Agreement, had or made for any Fee, Sum of Money, or Reward to be paid, as is aforeſaid, be adjudged a diſabled Perſons in the Law to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, to have,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cook. lib.</hi> 12.78.</note> occupy or enjoy the ſaid Office or Offices, Deputation or Deputations, or any part of any of them, for the which ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſhall ſo give or pay any Sum of Money, Fee or Reward, or make any Promiſe, Covenant, Bond or other Aſſurance, to give or pay any Sum of Money, Fee or Reward.</p>
               <p>And be it alſo Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every ſuch Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains, Sales, Promiſes, Bonds, Agreements, Covenants and Aſſurances as before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, ſhall be void, to and againſt Him and Them, by whom any ſuch Bargain, Sale, Bond, Promiſe, Covenant and Aſſurance ſhall be had or made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cook.</hi> Rep. Lib. 12.78. <hi>Hill.</hi> 8. <hi>Jac.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this very Term in the Caſe of Dr. <hi>Trevor,</hi> who was Chancellour of a Biſhop in <hi>Wales,</hi> it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved that the Office of a Chancellour and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, are within the Statute 5 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. The Words of which Statute are, <hi>Any Office,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which ſhall in any wiſe touch or concern the Adminiſtration or Execution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi> and the Words are ſtrongly Pen'd againſt Corruption of Officers, for they are, <hi>Which ſhall in any wiſe touch or concern the Adminiſtration,</hi> &amp;c. And the Preamble; <hi>And for avoiding of Corruption, which may hereafter happen to be in the Officers and Miniſters of thoſe Courts, Places, and Rooms, wherein there is requiſite to be had the true Adminiſtration of Justice, in Services of Truſt: And to the Intent that Perſons wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and meet to be advanced to the Places where Juſtice is to be Miniſtred, in any Service of Truſt to be Executed, ſhould be preferred to the ſame, and none other.</hi> Which Act being made for avoiding of Corruption in Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for the Advancement of Perſons more Worthy and ſufficient for to Execute the ſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by which Juſtice and Right ſhall be alſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51915:5"/>ſhall be Expounded moſt beneficially to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Corruption. And in as much as the Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows Eccleſiaſtical Courts to proceed in Caſe of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Hereſie, Schiſm, Incontinence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Loyalties of Matrimonies, of Divorce, of the Right of Tithes, Probat of Wills, granting of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that from theſe proceedings depend not only the Salvation of Souls, but alſo the Legitimation of Iſſues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that no Debt or Duty can be recovered by Executors, or Adminiſtrators, without Probat of Teſtaments, or Letters of Adminiſtrations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of great conſequence; It is moſt reaſon that ſuch Officers which concern the Adminiſtration and Execution of Juſtice in theſe Points, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Salvation of Souls, and the other matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſhall be within this Statute, than Officers which concern the Adminiſtration or Execution of Juſtice in Temporal matters; for this, that Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Offices in the ſaid Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, is more dangerous than the Officers in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Cauſes; for the Temporal Judge commits the Party Convict to the Goaler, but the Spiritual Judge commits the Perſon Excommunicate to the Devil. Alſo thoſe Officers do not only touch and concern the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But alſo are Services of great Truſt, for this, that the principal End of their proceedings is, <hi>Pro Salute Animarum, &amp;c.</hi> And there is no Exceptors or Proviſo in the Statute for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was reſolved that ſuch Offices were within the</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view <hi>of the ſaid Statute.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51915:5"/>
               <head>Here follows the Duty of a Goaler to his Priſoners, with his and other Officers Fees due by Law.</head>
               <p>BY the Common Law we find, as <hi>Bracton</hi> Lib. 3. fol. 105. <hi>Goalers are ordained to hold Priſoners, not to puniſh them.</hi> For Impriſonment by the Law is (neither ought to be) no more than a bare reſtraint of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, without thoſe illegal and unjuſt Diſtinctions of cloſe and open Priſon (as is uſual) See <hi>Stamf.</hi> Ple. Cro. fol. 70.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Cook</hi> in his 3 Inſt. 91. ſaith, <hi>That if the Goaler keep the Priſoners more ſtreightly then he ought of right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Britton fol. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Priſoner dieth, this is Felony in the Goaler by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law. And this is the Cauſe, That if a Priſoner dye in Priſon, the Coroner ought to ſit upon him.</hi> See alſo the ſaid <hi>Cook</hi> Fol. 34. <hi>Cap. Petty Treaſon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Flet. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> how Priſoners are to be uſed wherein is alſo an account of an Indictment of a Goaler for evil uſage of his Priſoner <hi>Fol.</hi> 35. <hi>in Trin. Term.</hi> 7. E. 3. <hi>cor Rege rot.</hi> 44.— That whereas one <hi>R. B.</hi> of <hi>T.</hi> was taken and detained in the Priſon of <hi>Lincoln</hi> Caſtle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> for a certain Debt of Statute Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, in the Cuſtody of <hi>T. B.</hi> Conſtable of the Caſtle <hi>L.</hi> aforeſaid; That the ſaid <hi>T. B.</hi> put the ſaid <hi>R.</hi> into the Common-Goal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Thieves, in a filthy Priſon, contrary to the form of the Statute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there detained him, till he had paid him a Fine of 40 s. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Cook</hi> makes this Obſervation, <hi>So as hereby it appeareth, where the Law requireth that a Priſoner ſhould be kept in ſafe and ſure Custody; yet that muſt be without any pain or torment to the Priſoner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Co.</hi> 3. Inſt. 52. ſaith, <hi>If a Priſoner by the Dures, that is hard uſage of the Goaler, cometh to untimely Death, this is Murther in the Goaler.</hi> And in the Law implieth Malice, in reſpect of the Cruelty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Horn,</hi> in the Mirror of Juſtice, page 288. ſaith, <hi>That it is an Abuſion of the Law, that Priſoners are put into Irons, or other pain, before they are Attainted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See alſo <hi>Cook</hi> 3. Inſt. 34, 35.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Horn</hi> alſo pag. 34, 36. Reckons the ſtarving of Priſoners by Famine, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vox plebis</hi> par. 1. f. 55, 56.</note> to be among the Crimes of <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide</hi> in a Goaler.</p>
               <p>Which alſo <hi>Cook</hi> in his 3 Inſt. Chap. 29. Title of <hi>Felony</hi> in <hi>Goalers</hi> by <hi>Dures</hi> of Impriſonment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Statute and by the Common Law. <hi>fo.</hi> 91.</p>
               <p>And next, let us ſee what the Law ſaith for the Fees due to Goalers. The Mirror of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> pag. 288. tells us, That it is an Abuſion of the Law, that Priſoners or others for them, to <hi>pay</hi> any thing for their <hi>Entries</hi> into the Goal, or for their <hi>Going out:</hi> This is the Common Law, there is no Fee due to them by the Common Law. See what the Statutes ſay, The Statute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 26. ſaith. <q>That no Sheriff, or other Miniſter of the King, ſhall take Reward for doing their Offices, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51915:6"/>what they take of the King, if they do they ſhall ſuffer double to the Party aggrieved, and be puniſhed at the will of the King.</q> Under this word, <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> are included, <hi>all Eſcheators, Coroners, Goalers, and the like.</hi> See <hi>Cook</hi> 2 Inſt. fol. 209. affirms. And agreeable is <hi>Stampf. pl. Coron.</hi> 49. Nay by the Statute of 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Chap. 10. Goalers are to receive <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Fellons,</hi> taking nothing by way of Fees for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of them. So odious is this Extortion of Goalers that very Thieves and Felons are exempt from payment of Fees.</p>
               <p>And we find in our Law-Books, That no Fees are due to any Officer, Goaler, or Miniſter of Juſtice, but only thoſe which are given by Act of Parliament, for if a Goaler will preſcribe for any Fees, the Preſcription is void, becauſe againſt this Act of Parliament, made 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. being an Act made within time of Memory, and takes away all manner of pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fees before; and we are ſure none can be raiſed by colour of preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſince: And therefore we find by the Books of 8. <hi>E.</hi> 4. fol. 18. <hi>That a Marſhal or Goaler cannot detain any Priſoner after his diſcharge from the Court, but only for the Fees of the Court</hi> (the Court being not barred by this Statute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. aforementioned) <hi>and if he do, he may be Indicted for Extortion.</hi> And agreeable to this is the Book of 21 F. 7. Fol. 16. where amongſt other things it's held for Law, <hi>That if a Goaler or Guardian of a Priſon, takes his Priſoners proper Garment, Cloak, or Money from him, it is a Treſpaſs, and the Goaler ſhall be anſwerable for it:</hi> So that we may undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably conclude, That there is no Fee at all due to any <hi>Goaler</hi> or <hi>Guardian</hi> of a Priſon from the Priſoner, but what is due unto him by ſpecial Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>And if a Goaler or Guardian of a Priſon, ſhall take any thing as a Fee of his Priſoner, he may and ought to be <hi>Indicted</hi> of <hi>Extortion,</hi> and upon Conviction to be removed from his Office; and if his Priſoner, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, Menace, or Dures, be enforced to give him Money; he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that Money againſt the Goaler again, in an Action of the Caſe at Common Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The King Conſidering the great Perjury, Extortion,<note place="margin">Stat. 23. <hi>H.</hi> 6. Chap. 10.</note> and Oppreſſion, which be and have been in this Realm by his Sheriffs, Under-Sheriffs, and their Clarks,<note place="margin">Stat. 4. <hi>H.</hi> 4, 5.</note> Bailiffs, and Keepers of Priſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath ordained by Authority aforeſaid, in eſchewing all ſuch Extortion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Raſt.</hi> predict. fol. 318.</note> Perjury, and Oppreſſion, that no Sheriff ſhall let to Farm in any manner his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor any of his Bailiwicks. Nor that any of the ſaid Officers and Miniſters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cook.</hi> predict. 365.</note> by occaſion, or under colour of their Office, ſhall take any other thing by them,<note place="margin">21. <hi>H.</hi> 7. fol. 16.</note> nor by any other perſon to their uſe, profit, or avail, if any perſon by them or any of them to be Arreſted or Attached, for the omitting of any Arreſt or Attachment to be made by their Body, or of any perſon by them, or any of them (by force or colour of their Office Arreſted or Attached) for Fine, Fee, Suit of Priſon, Mainpriſe, letting to Bail, or ſhewing any Eaſe or Favour (to any ſuch Perſon Arreſted or to be Attached) for their Reward or Profit; but ſuch as follow, that is to ſay, For the Sheriff 20 <hi>d.</hi> The Officer which maketh the Arreſt or Attachment, 4 <hi>d.</hi> And the Goaler of the Priſon if he be committed to Ward,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Raſt.</hi> predict. fol. 371.</note> 4 <hi>d.</hi>—And that all Sheriffs, Bailiffs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51915:6"/>Goalers, or any other Officer or Miniſters, which do contrary to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, in any Point of the ſame, ſhall loſe to the Party in this behalf indammaged or grieved, his treble Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,<note place="margin">Stat. 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> o.</note> and ſhall forfeit the Sum of 40 <hi>l.</hi> for every ſuch Offence, the one Moiety to the King, the other to the Proſecutor, to be Recovered at Common Law, in either of the Courts of Kings-Bench, or <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a perfect Account of the Goalers Fees in all Caſes, where Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are laid in Priſon upon Civil Matters and Cauſes, which Fee of 4 <hi>d.</hi> is more then any other Statute or Law allows them to take from their Priſoners: But in ſuch Caſes where the King is Party, it's eſtabliſhed, <q>That the Priſoners in all the Kings Priſons ſhould be maintained at the Kings Charge, and out of the Kings Revenues, according to the Old Law of the Land, much leſs to have Money extorted from him by the Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</q> But look into the Priſons in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> what horrible Oppreſſions, Extortions and Cruelties, are Exerciſed upon the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born People of <hi>England,</hi> yea in moſt Priſons throughout this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>So that by the Laws of the Land it appears, that thoſe who ſell, or take any manner of Reward for any Publick Office or Place, or thoſe who do receive any greater Fee than therein is expreſt, have no more Property, Right or Intereſt to do it, than the Pirate has to the peaceable Merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Ship, a Robber to the innocent Traveller's Purſe, or the Wolf to the blood of the harmleſs Lamb.</p>
               <p>All which is moſt humbly ſubmitted to the ſerious Conſideration of this Honourable Houſe, That the ſaid Matters may be referr'd to a Committee who ſhall be empowered to receive ſuch humble Propoſals as ſhall be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for a laſting proviſion to prevent the practice of the like Enormities and Cruelties; the which, as it will be pleaſing to the Great God of Juſtice and Mercy, will be of General Relief to the Oppreſſed, a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Honour to the Kingdoms Noble Patriots, and of General Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to Trade and Traders.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Licenſed,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 14, 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
